(DOCTOR WHO THEME)
Is the local radiation completely absorbed?
本地的辐射已经完全被吸收了吗？
Yes, its energy's been transferred to our fuel reserves.
是的, 它的能量已经转移到我们的燃料储备里了
- But we need much more.
- Of course. That is why we are here.
- 但我们还需要更多 - 当然, 那正是我们来这里的原因
With respect, Navigator Rago,
恕我直言, 导航员 Rago
I still consider we should have continued to Epsilon 4.
我仍然认为我们应该继续探索Epsilon 4号星
I decided otherwise, Probationer Toba.
我做了另外的决定, 实习生 Toba
But this planet has never been fully surveyed.
但这个星球从来没有完整勘察过
It's suitable for our purpose.
The planetary crust is thin here
它很适合我们的目的．这里的地壳很薄
and there's an intelligent form of life
suitable for a workforce.
还有智慧生命可以充当工人
But the natives may not be suitable for slave labour.
Suppose they're hostile?
但本星球人可能用作劳工。假如他们怀有敌意呢？
- If necessary, we shall destroy them.
- Yes, destroy them.
- 必要的话, 我们可以消灭他们  - 是的, 消灭他们
But only if necessary!
Commence work on the preliminary survey.
但只在非常必要的情况下！开始进行初步勘察吧
Command accepted.
接受命令
(WHOOSHING)
(LAUGHING)
Oh, yes. Oh, yes.
噢, 对了, 噢, 对了
(YAWNING)
- Are you still feeling tired, Doctor?
- Yes, just a little bit weary, Jamie.
- 你还是觉得疲惫吗, 博士  - 是的, 有那么一点, Jamie
It's a very exhausting business
真是个很累人的事情
projecting all those mental images, you know.
要投射那么多意识印象
- You need a good rest, Doctor.
- Yes, we all do. A nice holiday.
- 你需要好好休息一下, 博士  - 是, 我们都需要一个美好的假日
Where did you say this place was again?
你刚才说这个地方是哪儿？
Well, the scanner screen in the Tardis
showed it as an island of some sort
哦, TARDIS 里面的扫描屏幕显示出这像是一个岛
surrounded by a sea of mist.
周边是一片薄雾的海洋
Yes, it's an island on Dulkis,
a perfectly splendid planet.
是, 这是 Dulkis 上面的一个岛．Dulkis 是个非常漂亮的星球
I've heard that one before.
我以前听说过
And there won't be any Cybermen or Daleks, will there?
这里不会有赛博人、Dalek 什么的吧, 会吗？
(LAUGHS) No, no, no, of course not.
There's nothing unpleasant on Dulkis.
不, 不, 不, 当然没有．Dulkis上面没有什么让人不愉快的东西
Quarks, destroy the alien vessel.
Quarks, 摧毁那艘外星飞船
(QUARKS BEEPING)
(BUZZING)
Did you say these people were peaceful, Doctor?
你刚才说这里的人都很平和, 博士？
(STUTTERING) Oh, yes, Zoe,
the Dulcians are gentle and friendly.
哦, 是的, Zoe．Dulkis 人都是谦和友好的
Aye, it sounded like it!
是, 听起来像是！
- Did the explosion cause this?
- Oh, no, no, no.
- 是爆炸导致的吗？  - 噢, 不, 不, 不
This was caused by an explosion some time ago, Jamie.
这是好久以前的爆炸导致的, Jamie
Looks like atomic blast damage to me.
我看着像是原子弹爆炸造成的
Yes, I think you're right, Zoe.
是的, 我觉得你说得对, Zoe
But I don't understand it.
但我搞不懂了
Let's look inside, shall we?
我们进去看看, 好吗？
Mind the stuff here.
小心这里的东西
And you destroyed this travel ship?
你摧毁那艘旅行船没有？
You gave me no order to the contrary.
你没有给过我相反的命令啊
You are a probational navigator.
你是一个见习导航员
Your first task is to investigate. Second, assess.
你的第一任务是勘察, 第二, 评估
You allowed your instinct for destruction
你容许了让你那破坏的本能
- to interfere with your primary tasks.
- Not accepted. I did...
- 干扰了你的首要任务  - 不接受．我的确...
How can you assess that which does not exist?
你怎么能够对并不存在的东西进行评估呢？
Have you completed your atomic analysis?
你已经完成原子分析了吗？
Analysis complete.
分析已经完成
Atomic energy released on this island 17.2 decades ago.
这个岛上的原子能量是在 172 年前释放的
A long time. Strange that this should be
the only trace of radiation on this planet.
好久了．奇怪的是这是这个星球上唯一的辐射痕迹
Continue.
继续
Drilling sites have now been located and marked.
钻探地点都已经找到并标记出来了
Then we will examine them.
那我们去检查一下
Did you check the radiation level
before we left the Tardis?
在我们离开 TARDIS 之前我们检查过辐射水平了吗？
That's just what I was thinking, Zoe.
I think I did.
我也正在想这个问题, Zoe．我觉得我检查过了
- Yes, I'm sure I did.
- Hey, what are you two on about?
- 是的, 我确定我检查过了  - 嘿, 你们俩在讨论什么呢？
Well, I was just thinking.
哦, 我只是在想
This place reminds me
of the old atom test islands on Earth.
这个地方让我想起了地球上用于原子弹试验的那些岛屿
Yes. Yes, I think you're right, Zoe.
是的, 是的, 我想你是对的, Zoe
- Test islands?  - For atomic weapons, Jamie.
- 试验岛？  - 用于原子武器的, Jamie
But why on Dulkis?
但为什么 Dulkis 上会有？
They've outlawed war.
No, there must be some other explanation.
他们已经宣布战争为非法了．不, 肯定有其它的解释
Well, I vote we go back to the Tardis
and find somewhere else.
好啦, 我提议我们回到 TARDIS 去, 另外找个地方
Doctor!
博士！
TOBA: This is the eastern drilling site.
这是东端钻取点
- What is that?
- Just a crude, box-like structure.
- 那是什么  - 只是一个天然形成的盒子模样的东西
Shall I summon the Quarks to destroy it?
需要我把 Quarks 唤过来摧毁它吗？
Why? Will it interfere with the work?
为什么？它会干扰我们工作吗？
No, but...
不会, 但是...
Then it would be wasteful to destroy it.
那去摧毁它就是种浪费
(ALL EXCLAIMING)
- Oh, my beautiful coat is all wet.
- Ridiculous.
- 噢, 我漂亮的外套全湿了  - 荒谬
All this is totally unnecessary, you know.
所有这些都是完全没必要的, 知道吗
There's not a trace of contamination on us.
我们身上没有任何污染的痕迹
Yes, so I've noticed. It's odd, isn't it?
是的, 我也注意到了．很奇怪, 对吧？
- What's odd about it?
- Well, the whole island is radioactive.
- 有什么奇怪的？  - 哦, 整个岛都充满了辐射
It has been for 172 years. You must know that.
都已经 172 年了, 你肯定也知道
- Well, it isn't now.  - Of course it is.
- 但, 现在它没有  - 当然有
- Have you checked?  - TEEL: Well, not yet.
- 你检查过了吗？  - 是哦, 还没有
We've only just arrived.
我们才刚刚到这里
But we're taking the annual readings
during the next few days.
但我们要在接下来的几天采集年度数值
Well, if I were you, I'd take them now.
哦, 如果我是你, 我现在就采
Oh, my beautiful trousers.
噢, 我漂亮的裤子
I wasn't aware that anyone else
我倒不知道还会有其他人
had permission to work on the island except ourselves.
有权限在这个岛上工作
Tell me exactly what has been happening.
告诉我到底发生了什么？
But I was hoping you were going to tell us that.
但我还指望你能告诉我们呢
This is an atom test island, isn't it?
这个岛是用于原子弹试验的, 对不？
Oh, but of course. Everybody knows that.
哦, 当然了, 每个人都知道这个
Oh, well, we don't.
哦, 但是, 我们不知道
But atomic weapons on Dulkis?
但是 Dulkis 上面有原子武器？
- I thought war had been abolished here.
- It has.
- 我以为这里已经禁止战争了  - 是禁了
You seem to know surprisingly little
about your own planet.
对于你们自己的星球, 你们似乎知道得出奇的少
Well, that's it, you see.
We've just come in the Tar...
啊, 事实是, 你看, 我们刚刚到达...
Well, as Jamie was about to say,
嗯, 正如 Jamie 刚要说的
we come from a different world, from a different time.
我们来自另外一个世界, 另外一个时间
Not from this world? Really, that's very interesting.
不是来自这个世界？真的吗, 那可真有意思
I must note that in my daily report.
我必须把这个记在我的日报里
Well, you don't sound very surprised.
诶, 你似乎并不感到奇怪
Well, it does explain how you came to
expose yourself to the dangers on this island.
嗯, 这倒的确解释了你们为何让自己暴露于这个岛的危险之中
No Dulcian would do such a foolish thing.
没有那个 Dulkis 人会干这种蠢事
Well, what are you doing here, then?
哦, 那你在这里做什么呢？
We're part of Educator Balan's
expedition from the university.
我们是探险队的, 由大学教育家 Balan带队
But when I was here some time ago,
you were a peaceful race.
但我以前到这里的时候, 你们还是一个和平的种族
- So you've been here before?
- Well, yes.
- 你以前来过这里？  - 嗯, 是的
Ah, I must put that in my...
I'm so sorry. You were saying?
啊, 我必须把这个记进...对不起, 你刚才说什么？
Well, what's happened to you? I thought
aggressive weapons had been abolished.
嗯, 你们发生了什么事？我还以为攻击性武器已经被废止了
Oh, indeed they have.
The second council under Director Olvin.
哦, 他们的确禁了, Olvin 理事的第二议会
He banned the manufacture of all weapons.
他禁掉了所有武器的生产制造
Then what are you doing letting off
atomic devices all over the place?
那你们把原子设备弄得到处都是, 是在做什么呢？
Oh! Oh, there was only one explosion.
哦！ 哦, 只出现了一次爆炸．
Perhaps my pupil, Kando, should explain.
也许我的学生 Kando 可以做出解释
Let's see how much you remember, my dear.
让我们看看你记得多少, 我亲爱的
- Um... Oh, yes.  - The seventh council...
- 唔...噢, 是的  - 第七议会...
The seventh council under Director Manus
由 Manus 领导的第七议会
initiated research which lead to
the development of atomic energy.
启动了科学研究, 从而开始了原子能的发展
- The des...
- BALAN: Destructive capabilities.
- 破... - 破坏能力
The destructive capabilities of this
were immediately apparent and...
这个决定的破坏能力随即出现了, 于是...
BALAN: This island...
这座岛...
And this island was used
to test an explosive device,
于是就用这座岛测试了一次爆炸装置
the results of which can be seen today.
爆炸的结果至今可见到
Thereafter, all further research
into this type of energy was prohibited,
于是, 关于这类能量的所有后续研究都被禁止了
and the island kept as both a museum
and warning for future generations.
这座岛保留成了博物馆, 同时也向后代提供警示作用
Oh, well, she certainly does her homework.
哦, 嗯, 她显然是做了功课的
I see. Then this is an atomic test site?
我明白了．那这就是一个原子试验场了？
Oh, yes. You see, students...
That was really very good, Kando.
噢, 是的．你看, 学生们...这真的很不错, Kando
Students are brought here
to test the radiation level
学生们是被带到这里来测量辐射水平的
and observe the effect on the vegetation.
同时观察植物的生长情况
And of course, to see for themselves
the horrors of atomic destruction.
当然了, 也是为了亲眼看看原子能可怕的毁灭能力
- So there should be radioactivity here?
- But there isn't.
- 所以这里应该是有辐射的？  - 但这里没有
No. I wonder why?
没有．我想问为什么？
Explain.
解释一下
Part of this collection of crude weapons.
原始武器收藏品中的其中一件
Continue.
继续
This one operates on the early laser principle.
这一个依赖于早期的激光原理运作
Fire mechanism here.
这里是开火机关
Self-charging power cell. Limited range.
自动充电电池．射程有限
Is this all you notice?
你留意到的只有这些吗？
The other weapons are just as simple.
其它的武器也一样原始
There's nothing here that could threaten us.
这里没有什么东西能威胁到我们
- These things are so old that if...
- Precisely. Old.
- 这些东西是如此古老以至于..  - 正是, 古老
At last, you casually mention a fact
of major significance.
至少，你无意中提到一个非常重要的事实
Has it not occurred to you,
Probationer Toba,
你有没有想过, 实习生 Toba
that other weapons
must have been developed since these?
在这些武器之后肯定有其它武器发展出来了？
Agreed, Navigator Rago.
同意, 导航员 Rago
DOCTOR: But why do you think
we might be responsible? Thank you.
但是为什么你们觉得我们应该负责？谢谢你
Well, it is conceivable that your craft, the...
是啊, 很容易想到是你们的飞船, 那个...
- Tardis.  -...Tardis,
- TARDIS  - 那个 TARDIS
could have attracted the radioactivity
可能吸收了这些辐射
in much the same way as a magnet attracts metal.
就像一块磁铁吸附金属那样
(CHUCKLES) Oh, it would have registered.
- Do spacecraft often land in Dulkis?
- As far as I know, you are the first.
- 经常有飞船降落在 Dulkis 吗？ - 就我所知, 你们是第一个
I must say, then,
you don't seem the least bit surprised.
那, 我必须说, 你们似乎一点也不惊讶
We are taught to accept fact,
我们早被教导为接受事实
it being foolish to contemplate fantasy
in the face of reality.
在现实面前琢磨那些假想的事情是愚蠢的
You are here. This is fact.
你们到了这里, 这就是事实
That you come from another planet I accept,
你们来自于另外一个星球, 这我接受
because I have no other means of proving it.
因为我也没有其它手段来证明
- TEEL: Not a sign of radiation.
- BALAN: There.
- 一点辐射也没有  - 那里
But look what I found.
看看我找到了什么？
- Cully, what are you...
- Never mind that now.
- Cully, 你在做... - 先别管那个
We've got to get back to the capital.
我们得回到首都去
Oh, it's impossible.
We haven't even begun our survey yet.
噢, 这不可能．我们都还没有开始我们的调查
Well, if you don't, you'll be wiped out.
但是, 如果你们不回去, 你们全都会被消灭的
He claims to have seen robots and spacecraft.
他宣称说看到了机器人和飞船
- You didn't tell me you brought robots.
- I haven't.
- 你没有告诉我你还带了机器人来  - 我没带
Look, I brought three people here in my ship.
听着, 我的飞船就带了三个人到这里来
They've been killed by those creatures.
So if you don't...
他们被那些家伙杀死了．所以如果你不...
(LAUGHING)
- ZOE: What's so funny?
- Now, I see. Ajest.
- 什么这么好笑？  - 啊, 我明白了．笑话
Three people. So you come
from another world, do you, Doctor?
三个人．所以你们是从另外一个世界来的, 是吗, 博士？
- Hey, I don't think...
- Really, Cully,
- 嘿, 我不认为...  - 真的, Cully
you and your friends might at least
have agreed upon the same story.
你和你的朋友们至少应该先勾兑一下故事的说法
What? But these aren't my three, you old...
什么？但这并不是我那三个人, 你个老...
Oh, what's the use?
哦, 这是做什么用的？
- JAMIE: What was he talking about?
- I don't know.
- 他在说什么啊？  - 我不知道
Look, I've never seen
this gentleman before in my life.
听着, 我这辈子从来没见过这位先生
Cully, you had no right to bring
these people here without permission,
Cully, 你不能未获得任何授权就带这三个人到这里来
even if you are the son
of the director of the council.
即便你是议长的儿子也不行
Well, go on, then.
Why don't you call him up?
好, 那就去啊．你为什么不给他打电话？
At least he's not as stupid as you are.
至少他不像你这么蠢
- You say you've seen a spacecraft?
- I've told you, haven't I?
- 你说你看见了一艘飞船？  - 我跟你说过吧？
And robots. Well, at least I think
they were robots.
还有机器人．哦, 至少我认为它们是机器人
What exactly did this spacecraft look like?
那艘飞船具体是什么样子的？
Well, it's large and circular
and a sort of silvery colour.
哦, 巨大的圆形, 带着某种银色
That means it can't be the Tardis.
那就是说不可能是我们的 TARDIS
Are you sure it wasn't square,
like a large wooden box?
你确定它不是方的, 看起来像一个木头盒子？
No, no, that's not the spacecraft.
不, 不, 那不是我说的飞船
No, the box is where
those aliens have made a sort of mark,
不, 那些外星人在那个盒子附近做了某种标记
a five-pointed star.
像一颗５个点的星形
They were examining it just now.
Talking about destroying it.
他们正在检查那个盒子, 在讨论是否摧毁它
- What?  - What?
- 什么？  - 什么？
- Jamie, we better go and see.
- Come on.
- Jamie, 我们最好去看看  - 快点
You're wasting your time.
你这是在浪费时间
I prefer to make up my own mind, thank you.
我更喜欢自己做决定, 谢谢你了
Jamie. Are you coming, Zoe?
Jamie. 你来吗, Zoe?
- No, I think I'll stay here.  - Right.
- 不, 我觉得我还是留在这里  - 好
- Come on, then.
- We shan't be a minute.
- 快点, 来  - 我们马上就来
Commence work on preparing the sites
of the outer bore hole.
开始为外面的钻孔做准备工作
- At once, Navigator Rago.
- Send this message to Fleet Leader.
- 马上, 导航员 Rago  - 发送下述消息给舰队头目
"Materials located. Detailed report follows."
"已经定位到材料．详细报告随后提交＂
Command accepted.
接受命令
JAMIE: At least they haven't harmed the Tardis.
至少他们还没有伤害 TARDIS
DOCTOR: That's a relief.
这放心了
Jamie, come and have a look at this.
It's interesting.
Jamie, 过来看看这个, 很有意思
- Look. See. - What?
- 喏, 看到没  - 什么?
What's so interesting about that?
哪有什么奇怪的？
Well, I think it must be
some sort of survey mark.
这个, 我觉得这是在做某种勘察留下的印记
Very likely.
很有可能
Jamie, look.
Jamie, 看
- Some sort of tracks.  - So they are.
- 像是某种脚印  - 还真是
We'll follow them, shall we?
我们跟踪一下, 该跟吗？
Oh, look, I think we'd better get back.
噢, 你看, 我觉得我们最好回去
Zoe will be wondering what's happening...
Zoe可能在嘀咕我们怎么样了...
Well, this is interesting. Yes.
嗯, 这有点意思, 是的
Obviously an interstellar spaceship
of considerably advanced design.
显然这艘星际飞船有着相当先进的设计
Oh, no. You're not thinking
what I think you're thinking, are you?
噢, 别, 你不是在想我觉得你在想的事情吧, 是吗？
That, I think, Jamie, depends
on what you think I am thinking.
那就, 我觉得, 取决于你觉得我在想什么
Oh.
哦
- Hey, Doctor. - Stop that, Jamie.
- 嘿, 博士  - 别那样, Jamie
- Doctor. - Jamie, don't do it.
- 博士  - Jamie, 别那样
- Doctor, look. Look.  - Oh, my word.
- 博士, 看, 看  - 噢, 天啦
QUARK: Do not move. Do not move.
不许动, 不许动
Next task?
下个任务是？
Shall we destroy?
需要我们消灭吗？